Guide to the National Smokejumper Association Records 1919-2010
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
National Smokejumper Association Records
1919-2010
University of Montana--Missoula Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library K. Ross Toole Archives The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/dept/arch/arch.htm library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 620
National Smokejumper Association
3.20 linear feet
The collection contains reports, correspondence, interviews, personal papers, photographs, films, and publications related to the development and history of aerial fire management. The collection primarily includes papers and publications created by the National Smokejumper Association as well as the papers of individual smokejumpers and a collection of papers of the U.S. Forest Service documenting the early development of aerial fire management.
Historical Note
The National Smokejumper Association (NSA) is an organization which preserves and shares the history of aerial fire management and provides a forum for those associated with wildland firefighting. The NSA maintains a roster of current and former smokejumpers and actively collects the history of individuals and organizations associated with the history of smoke jumping and aerial fire management. The National Smokejumper Association exists as of 2005.
The collection contains reports, correspondence, rosters, personal papers, oral histories, photographs, and films documenting the history of aerial fire management. The majority of the material in the collection was created by the association itself, by former smokejumpers or by the U.S. Forest Service. The collection includes materials regarding the development of parachute jumping during the F Studies – Aerial Control Parachute Jumping experiments of the late 1930s and early 1940s by the U.S. Forest Service. The collection also contains fire reports from various years including the investigation report regarding Mann Gulch, Montana (1949) as well as newsletters and magazines published by the National Smokejumper Association and contains numerous other magazine articles related to the development and history of smoke jumping and aerial fire management. The collection contains personal papers of individual smokejumpers including those of Bob Brennan, a smokejumper trained at Nine Mile Base (Montana) in 1941. This collection documents the importance of smoke jumping and provides personal accounts as well as early government information about exploration and development of wild land firefighting.
Series I, the National Smokejumper Association Records, primarily contains copies of the organization’s newsletter, Static Line Static Line, and their magazine, Smokejumper Quarterly. It also includes a report of the Long Range Plan of the organization written in 2002 as well as reunion lists and copies of email correspondence about the organization.
Series II, History of Smoke jumping, comprises the bulk of the collection and is arranged chronologically within five subseries with the exception of Subseries 2: Personal Narratives, which is arranged alphabetically by individual, subject or organization. Subseries 1: Reports, Handbooks, and Manuals, is a chronological sequence of materials documenting a range of topics related to aerial fire management. Materials include fire reports, specifically a copy of the investigation of the Mann Gulch fire (1949) and the fire investigation report of the South Canyon Fire on Storm King Mountain (1994). Subseries 1 also includes safety manuals, the annual reports of Siskiyou Smokejumper base (1971 – 1980), a draft copy of a smokejumper study of Region 6 (1984), and trail maintenance reports. Subseries 2: Personal Narratives, is arranged alphabetically by last name or by organization and contains publications of rosters arranged chronologically, first-hand accounts, interviews and oral histories of the experiences of individual smoke jumpers as well as published narratives of individuals of specific regional smoke jumping stations including Cave Junction, Oregon (1944 – 50) and Region 4 (1940s) as well as narratives and copies of photographs of Civilian Public Service Fliers (1940s). Materials also include newspaper clippings, articles, obituaries, and photographs submitted by smokejumpers including a scrapbook of photographs of the Storm King Fire line (2000). Subseries 3: U.S. Forest Service Papers, documents the F Studies Aerial Fire Management Control Project (1940s) including papers related to the Civilian Public Service program and the technical developments of parachute jumping. Materials include memos, invoices, reports, correspondence and publications. Subseries 4: General Histories, contains overviews and timelines of major benchmarks in the history of smoke jumping. Items include booklets, chronologies, a conference paper and general histories of several regional smoke jumping stations including the North Cascades Smokejumper Base, the California Smokejumpers and the Siskiyou smokejumper base. Subseries 5: Articles/Clippings, includes published magazine and newspaper articles related to a broad range of topics about aerial fire management including several issues of National Geographic National Geographic ranging from 1950s – 1980s. Subseries 6: Memorabilia, primarily contains copies of books and movie posters (1930s – 1950s) related to fire fighting including books for children.
Series III contains the Papers of Bob Brennan, a smokejumper trained at Nine Mile Base in Montana. Materials include diaries, jump logs, and photographs of his experiences in 1941 stationed at Moose Creek Airport/Guard station as well as an audio tape recording of an oral history interview from later in life.
Series IV is arranged chronologically by the content of the material and contains film reels, video cassettes and photographs on CD. Materials include a 12 tape series entitled Wilderness Survival as well as a film reel of the Smithsonian project about Smokejumpers from the 1940s and a copy of the Wilderness Warrior video. The series also includes computer cassettes and photos on CD of the North Cascades Smokejumper Base as well as a film reel of William Moody’s jump during an exchange with Russia (1976).
This collection has been divided into five series:
Series I: National Smokejumper Association Records, 1978, 1993 – 2010, 0.75 linear feet
Subseries 1: Reports/Memos, 1993, 2002, 0.05 linear feet
Subseries 2: Correspondence, 1999-2003, 0.05 linear feet
Subseries 3: Reunions, 1978, 2004-2010, 0.05 linear feet
Subseries 4: Publications, 1997-2010, 0.5 linear feet
Series II: History of Smoke Jumping, 1910-2009, 1.75 linear feet
Subseries 1: Reports/Handbooks/Manuals, 1940-1994, 0.4 linear feet
Subseries 2: Personal Narratives, 1910-2009, 0.5 linear feet
Subseries 3: U.S. Forest Service, 1939-1999, 0.3 linear feet
Subseries 4: General Histories, 1940-1998, 0.15 linear feet
Subseries 5: Articles/Clippings, 1919-2005, 0.3 linear feet
Subseries 6: Memorabilia, 1930-1950, 0.1 linear feet
Series III: Personal Papers of Smokejumpers, 1938–1942, [1995], 0.2 linear feet
Subseries 1: Papers of Bob Brennan, 1938–1942, [1995], 0.2 linear feet
Series IV: Audiovisual, 1939–1940, 1976, 2004, 0.8 linear feet
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of the K. Ross Toole Archives, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Prior to the records coming to the Archives, the collection had been in the possession of the National Smokejumper Association.
Gift of National Smokejumper Association Board in 2003.
Additions to the collection are ongoing and will be added by the organization and individual donors.
Two oral history collections held at the K. Ross Toole Archives and Special Collections contain several oral history interviews with smokejumpers: OH 133, Smokejumper Oral History Project, and OH 163, Civilian Public Service Smokejumpers Oral History Project.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
United States. Forest Service
Aeronautics in forest fire control--United States--History; Mann Gulch Fire, Mont., 1949; Parachuting--United States--History; Smokejumpers--United States; Smokejumping--United States--History
Forestry and Forestry Products; Montana; Technology; Oregon; Washington (State)
- National Smokejumper Association Records, 1978; 1993-2010; Series I; 0.75 linear feet
  - Reports and Memos, 1993; 2002; Subseries 1; 0.05 linear feet
    - Memos and Clippings, 1993 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Stategic Plan, 2002 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Correspondence, 1999-2003; Subseries 2; 0.05 linear feet
    - Smokejumper History Project, 1999-2003 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Reunions, 1978; 2004-2010; Subseries 3; 0.05 linear feet
    - Reunions, 1978; 2004 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Publications, 1997-2010; Subseries 4; 0.5 linear feet
    - NSA Trail Maintenance Reports, 2001-2005 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - SmokejumperQuarterly, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2001 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2002 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2003 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2004 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2005 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2006 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2007 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2008 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2009 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Smokejumper Quarterly, 2010 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Static Line Newsletter, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 2/13)
- History of Smokejumping, 1910-2009; Series II; 1.75 linear feet
  - Reports/Handbooks/Manuals, 1940-2004; Subseries 1; 0.4 linear feet
    - Aerial Fire Control Project Region One, 1940 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - District #9 – Forest Patrol, 1941 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Smokejumper Project – Region Six, 1943 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Civil Air Regulations, 1945 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Report of the Board of Review, Mann Gulch Fire, 1949 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Higgins Ridge Fire, Nez Perce National Forest, 1961 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Training Manual Firefighting, 1962 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Annual Reports - Siskiyou Smokejumper Base, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - U.S. – U.S.S.R. Exchange, Technical Report Smoke Jumping/Repel, 1976 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - LOBE Parachute/EAGLE Parachute, Papers by David Gold, SAFE Symposium, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Smokejumper Study, Region Six, 1984 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Mann Gulch Fire That Couldn’t Be Won, 1993 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Report of South Canyon Fire Investigation, 1994 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Fire Behavior Associated with 1994 South Canyon Fire – Storm King Mountain, Colorado, 1998 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Personal Narratives, 1910-2009; Subseries 2; 0.05 linear feet
    - Roster of Forest Service Jumpers, 1940 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Roster of Retired Smokejumpers, 1945-1981 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Who’s Who in Region 4 Smokejumping, 1943-1997 (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Static Lines and Canopies, Stories from Smokejumpers, Civilian Public Service Camp, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Civilian Public Service Smokejumpers, Volume I, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Civilian Public Service Smokejumpers, Volume II, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Civilian Public Service Smokejumpers, Volume III, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Personal Narratives, 1940-1979 (Box-folder 4/8)
    - Personal Narratives, Unidentified Account, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
    - Interview with Jim "Smokey" Alexander, 193- (Box-folder 4/10)
    - H.P. Barringer, Forest Ranger, 1910 (Box-folder 4/11)
    - Mike Burke, Funeral Service Program and Photos, undated (Box-folder 4/12)
    - Ira Burton, Obituary, 2003 (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Gunter Dambro, Scrapbook of Photographs, Storm King Fire Line, 2000 (Box-folder 4/14)
    - Jerry Dixon, DVD – Ten Seconds Over Birch Hill, 1976-2009 (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Carroll Gambrell, Letter, 1994 (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Smokejumper Oral History Project, Max Glaves, Interview, 1984 (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Search for K. Reed Harrison, his wife Judy and daughter Julie, 1993 (Box-folder 4/18)
    - Brian C. Hicks, MSO, 1995 (Box-folder 4/19)
    - Smokejumper Oral History Project, Bruce Jackson, Interview, 1984 (Box-folder 4/20)
    - Smokejumper Oral History Project, Sherill King, Interview, 1985 (Box-folder 4/21)
    - John Lewis, Photographs, undated (Box-folder 4/22)
    - David Liston, Obituary, 199- (Box-folder 4/23)
    - Lester Lycklama, Smokejumper, 1946 (Box-folder 4/24)
    - Jack F. Matthews, Biographical Information and Clippings, undated (Box-folder 4/25)
    - H. Roger McPike, Inventory of Slides Taken 1953 – 1956 Region IV, undated (Box-folder 4/26)
    - Smokejumper Oral History Project, Charles Nyquist, Interview, 1984 (Box-folder 4/27)
    - Smokejumper Oral History Project, Diane Pryce, Interview, 1984 (Box-folder 4/28)
    - Bob Reid, Firsthand Account, MSO 57, undated (Box-folder 4/29)
    - Carroll Rieck, Reflections, undated (Box-folder 4/30)
    - Hank Shank, MSO 47, undated (Box-folder 4/31)
    - George K. Sisler, Congressional Medal of Honor, undated (Box-folder 4/32)
    - Kenneth Roy Smith, Smokejumper 1955, Obituary, undated (Box-folder 4/33)
    - Willi Unseold, Biography and Photos, undated (Box-folder 4/34)
    - Ed Summerfield, photos of him in smokejumper's gear, 1950 (Box-folder 4/35)
    - Astronauts, Information Summary, NASA, 1997 (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Pilots, 1940s, 1970-1989 (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Public Civil Service, Photographs, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Region Four, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Unit at Cave Junction, Photographs and Narrative, 1949-1950 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - United States Forest Service, 1939-1999; Subseries 3; 0.3 linear feet
    - U.S. Forest Service and Bureau of Land Management Smokejumpers, undated (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Forest Fire Fundamentals Booklet, undated (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Inventory of Photographs, 1939 (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Report on Parachute Jumping Experiment, Aerial Fire Control, 1939 (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Aerial Delivery of Supplies, 1939 (Box-folder 5/10)
    - History of Smokejumping, 1939, 1939 – 1949 (Box-folder 5/11)
    - F Studies Aerial Control, Memos and Correspondence, Jan 1940 – May 1940 (Box-folder 5/12)
    - F Studies Aerial Control, Memos and Correspondence, June 1940 – Dec 1940 (Box-folder 5/13)
    - F Studies Aerial Control, Memos and Reports, 1942 – 1949 (Box-folder 5/14)
    - Fire Control Handbook, Region 6, Part III Suppression, 1949 (Box-folder 5/15)
    - Air Operations Handbook, 1952 (Box-folder 5/16)
    - Specifications for Container for Smokejumper Backpack for Parachute Canopies, 1957 (Box-folder 5/17)
    - History of Smoke jumping, Region I, 1959 (Box-folder 5/18)
    - Narrative of the Smokejumpers, 1965 (Box-folder 5/19)
    - Press Release, Smokejumper Bases to be Studied, 1984 (Box-folder 5/20)
    - C-7 Field Evaluation, Apr – Oct 1994 (Box-folder 5/21)
    - FS-14 Parachute Report, Apr 6,1995 (Box-folder 5/22)
    - Escape Routes: An Anecdotal Evaluation, 1995 (Box-folder 5/23)
    - Aerial Delivered Fire Fighter Study Oct 1999 (Box-folder 5/24)
  - General Histories, 1940-1998; Subseries 4; 0.15 linear feet
    - Paper by Bruce VanVoorhis, n.d. (Box-folder 6/1)
    - Outline History of Siskiyou Smokejumper Project, 1943-1979 (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Chronology of Aerial Fire Management, Ch.6 of Malcolm Edward Hardy’s Masters Thesis, 1946 (Box-folder 6/3)
    - History of Smoke Jumping by the Aviation Aerial Management Booklet, 1980 (Box-folder 6/4)
    - History of Smoke jumping, 1980s (Box-folder 6/5)
    - The History of California Smokejumpers, 1997 (Box-folder 6/6)
    - History of the North Cascades Smokejumper Base by William Moody, 1998 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Articles/Clippings, 1919–2005; Subseries 5; 0.3 linear feet
    - Articles/Clippings, 1919 – 1989 (Box-folder 6/8)
    - Articles/Clippings, 1940s (Box-folder 6/9)
    - Articles/Clippings, 1950s (Box-folder 6/10)
    - Articles/Clippings, 1960s (Box-folder 6/11)
    - Articles/Clippings, 1970s (Box-folder 6/12)
    - Articles/Clippings, 1980s (Box-folder 6/13)
    - Articles/Clippings, 1990s (Box-folder 6/14)
    - Articles/Clippings, 2000s (Box-folder 6/15)
    - Articles/Clippings, n.d. (Box-folder 6/16)
    - National Geographic, June 1950 (Box-folder 6/17)
    - National Geographic, June 1952 (Box-folder 6/18)
    - National Geographic, Sept 1956 (Box-folder 6/19)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1961 (Box-folder 6/20)
    - National Geographic, July 1968 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - National Geographic, Sept 1982 (Box-folder 7/2)
    - National Geographic, Feb 1989 (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Life Magazine Article on Mann Gulch, 1949 (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Seattle Times, Sunday Pictorial, Parachuting to Work, A Smokejumper in Action, Aug 14, 1966 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - Memorabilia, 1930–1950; Subseries 6; 0.1 linear feet
    - Posters and Articles related to Smoke jumping and Firefighting, 1930s-1940s (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Stories on Smoke jumping and Firefighting for Children, 1940s-1950s (Box-folder 7/5)
- Personal Papers of Smokejumpers, 1938-1942, [1995]; Series III
  - Papers of Bob Brennan, 1938-1942, [1995]; Subseries 1; 0.2 linear feet
    - Jump Log, 1941 (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Diaries, 1938 – 1942 (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Photos, Slides, and Inventory, Nine Mile Base, MT, 1940s (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Oral History Cassette Tape, undated (Box-folder 7/9)
    - NSA Bumper Sticker and Membership Card, undated (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Photograph Album, 1940s (Box-folder 7/11)
- Audiovisual, 1939–1940, 1976, 1998, 2004; Series IV; 0.8 linear feet
  - Wilderness Survival Videotapes, 1998 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Photos on CD, North Cascades Smokejumper Base Honored at Seattle Mariner Game, Sept. 2004 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Photos on CD, North Cascades Smokejumper Base and National Forest Service Archives, undated (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Wilderness Warriors Smokejumpers, ESPN (21 min version), 1 Broadcast Videocassette, 1989 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Forest Service Experimental Smokejumper Project, Intercity Airport, Winthrop, WA, Film by Ferd Haase, 1939 – 1940 Smokejumpers, 1 reel of film, and 1master DVD copy and 1 DVD use copy of the film created by Photo Magic Video Productions in 2006 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Computers Disks, unidentified, undated (Box-folder 9/5)
  - William Moody, U.S. – U.S.S.R. Exchange Jump, 1 reel of film, 1976, and 1 master DVD copy and 1 DVD use copy of the film created by Photo Magic Video Productions in 2006 (Box-folder 10/1)